<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBk XML V4.4CR2//EN" 
 "file:///c:/home/xae-dev/xae/doctypes/docbook/docbookx.dtd" []>


<?xml-stylesheet href="file:///c:/home/jde-dev/jde/doc/src/styles/html/jdebook.xsl" type="text/xsl"  ?>

<book>

  <title>Debugging with jdb</title>


  <bookinfo>

    <releaseinfo>
      <remark>
	Revised for JDEE <productnumber>2.3.3</productnumber>
      </remark>
    </releaseinfo>

    <copyright>
      <year>1997</year>
      <year>1998</year>
      <year>1999</year>
      <year>2000</year>
      <year>2001</year>
      <year>2002</year>
      <year>2003</year>
      <holder>Paul Kinnucan</holder>
    </copyright>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter>

    <title><anchor id="Intro"/>Debugger Setup</title>

    <para>You should perform the following steps before attempting to use jdb.</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
	<para>Set the configuration variable
	  <varname>jde-debugger</varname> to <option>jdb</option> if
	  you are using version 1.3 (or later) of the Windows or
	  Solaris versions of the JDK or version 1.2.2 (or later) of
	  the Linux version of the JDK. Set
	  <varname>jde-debugger</varname> to <option>oldjdb</option>
	  if you are using older versions of the JDK.</para>
	</listitem>


      <listitem>
	  <para>
	    Use <varname>jde-sourcepath</varname> to specify the paths
	    of any source code that you expect to visit while
	    debugging your application (see <ulink
	      url="#SettingSourcePath"> 
	      Setting the Source Path</ulink>). If you suspect that a
	    problem is occurring in the Java API, you should include
	    the API source files in your source path.
	  </para>      
	</listitem>


    <listitem>
	  <para>	
	    Set <varname>jde-compile-option-debug</varname> on 
	    (see 
	    <ulink url="../jde-ug/jde-ug-content.html#CompilingJavaPrograms">Compiling 
	      Java Programs</ulink>). This causes the compiler to insert
	    information needed by the debugger into your
	    application's class files.
	  </para>      
	</listitem>

      <listitem>
	  <para>Specify the app's main class either by setting the
	    <varname>jde-run-application-class</varname> variable  or by starting the
	    debugger from the buffer that contains the source file for
	    the main class.
	  </para>      
	</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

  </chapter>

  <chapter>

    <title><anchor id="RunningDebugger"/>Running the Debugger</title>

    <sect3>

      <title><anchor id="StartingDebugger"/>Starting the Debugger</title>

      <para>To debug a program with <filename>jdb</filename>,
	first select a buffer containing the source of the program you
	want to debug (or a source buffer containing the program's
	main class if you have not set
	<varname>jde-run-application-class</varname>). Then execute
	the JDEE's <command>jde-debug</command> command. You can execute
	this command by:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Selecting 
	    <menuchoice>
	      <guimenu>JDE</guimenu>
	      <guimenuitem>Debug App</guimenuitem></menuchoice> 
	  </para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Entering the key combination 
	    <keycombo>
	      <keycap>C</keycap>
	      <keycap>c</keycap>
	    </keycombo> <keycombo>
	      <keycap>C</keycap>
	      <keycap>v</keycap></keycombo> <keycombo>
	      <keycap>C</keycap>
	      <keycap>d</keycap></keycombo>
	  </para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>Entering <keycombo>
	      <keycap>M</keycap>
	      <keycap>x</keycap></keycombo> <command>jde-debug</command></para>
	</listitem>
  
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The JDEE launches jdb, passing to it the name of the main
	class of the program in the current source buffer and any
	debug options that you have specified via the JDEE's debugger
	option variables (see <ulink
	  url="#SettingDebugOptions">Setting Debug Options</ulink>.
	jdb in turn launches a virtual machine to run the debuggee
	program and stops the virtual machine before the main method
	of the program's main class. Meanwhile the JDEE splits the
	source window into two windows.
      </para>

      <screenshot>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/debug1.gif"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para> 
	The upper window shows the source buffer.  The menu bar
	of the source buffer displays a menu (<guimenu>Jdb</guimenu>)
	of debug commands. The lower window shows the debugger
	interaction buffer.
      </para>

      <para>At this point, you can set breakpoints, run to a breakpoint that
      you set before you started the debugger, or step into the main method
      of your program.</para>


      <sect4>

	<title><anchor id="SettingDebugOptions"/>Setting Debug Options</title>

	<para>The <command>jde-jdb</command> command (selected by
	<menuchoice>
	    <guimenu>JDE</guimenu>
	    <guimenuitem>Debug App</guimenuitem></menuchoice> when jdb
	  is the debugger for the current project) can optionally pass
	  command-line arguments that specify various debug options to
	  jdb when starting jdb. The JDEE provides two ways to specify
	  these options: via customization variables or in the
	  minibuffer when you run the <command>jde-jdb</command>
	  command.</para>
      
	<para>The <command>jde-jdb</command> command passes any
	  options that you specify via customization variables to jdb.
	  In addition, if you set the customization variable
	  <varname>jde-db-read-vm-args</varname> to a non-nil value,
	  the <command>jde-jdb</command> command prompts you to enter
	  debugger options in the minibuffer. It appends the options
	  that you enter to the options specified via customization
	  variables. The JDEE saves the arguments that you enter in a
	  minibuffer history list. You can recall previously entered
	  options by pressing the up or down arrows on your keyboard.
	</para>

      </sect4>

      <sect4>

	<title><anchor id="SettingAppArguments"/>Setting App Arguments</title>

	<para>You can use the customization variable
	  <varname>jde-db-option-application-args</varname> to specify
	  arguments to be passed to the application launched by jdb.
	  The <command>jde-jdb</command> command inserts the specified
	  arguments on the command-line that it constructs to run
	  jdb.</para>

	<para>In addition, if you set the customization variable
	  <varname>jde-db-read-app-args</varname> to a
	  non-<option>nil</option> value, the
	  <command>jde-jdb</command> command prompts you to enter the
	  application arguments in the minibuffer. It appends the
	  options that you enter to the arguments specified via
	  <varname>jde-db-option-application-args</varname>. The JDEE
	  saves the arguments that you enter in a minibuffer history
	  list. You can recall previously entered options by pressing
	  the up or down arrows on your keyboard. </para>

    </sect4>

    </sect3>


    <sect3>

      <title><anchor id="EnteringCommands"/>Entering Debug Commands</title>

	<para>The JDE lets you enter commands from either the current source
	  buffer or from the debugger command-line interaction buffer.
	  You can enter all debugger commands from the debugger
	  buffer. You can enter only a subset of debugger commands
	  from the current source buffer. </para>

	<para> To enter a debugger command
	  from the current source buffer, select the command from the
	  jdb menu or type the shortcut key for the command. The <guimenu>Jdb</guimenu>
	  menu lists the shortcut keys
	  for debugger commands. </para>

 
	<para>To enter a command in the debugger interaction window, type the
	  command at the debugger prompt and press the <keycap>Enter</keycap>
	  key. To see a list of debugger commands, enter the command
	  <command>help</command>.
	</para>

    </sect3>

    <sect3>

      <title><anchor id="SteppingProgram"/>Stepping Through a Program</title>

      <para>
	Jdb provides a set of command-line commands that advance a
	program to the next line or the next breakpoint. The JDEE's
	jdb interface provides Emacs commands that invoke the jdb's
	step commands from a source buffer and move a debug cursor to
	the next line to be executed in the source buffer.  If you
	prefer, you can enter jdb's step commands directly in the jdb
	buffer. 
      </para>

      <sect4>

	<title><anchor id="StepCommands"/>Step Commands</title>

	<para> The following table lists the jdb step commands
	  supported by the JDEE.
	</para>

	<table>
	  <title>Step Commands</title>
	  <tgroup cols="4">
	    <thead>
	      <row>
		<entry>Jdb Menu Item</entry>
		<entry>Emacs Command</entry>
		<entry>jdb Command</entry>
		<entry>Description</entry>
	      </row>
	    </thead>
	    <tbody>
	      <row>
		<entry>Step Over</entry>
		<entry>jde-bug-step-over</entry>
		<entry>next</entry>
		<entry><para>Advance to the next line in the current
		    method, stepping over any lines that invoke other
		    methods.</para></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Step Into</entry>
		<entry>jde-debug-step-into</entry>
		<entry>step</entry>
		<entry><para>Advance to the next line in the
		    program.</para></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Step Out</entry>
		<entry>jde-debug-step-out</entry>
		<entry>step up</entry>
		<entry><para>Advance to the next line in the method
		    that invoked the current method.</para></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Continue</entry>
		<entry>jde-debug-cont</entry>
		<entry>cont</entry>
		<entry><para>Advance to the next breakpoint or to the
		    end of the program, whichever comes
		    first.</para></entry>
	      </row>
	    </tbody>
	</tgroup>
	</table>

      </sect4>

      <sect4>

	<title><anchor id="DebugCursor"/>Debug Cursor</title>

	<para>The JDEE uses an arrow, called the debug cursor, to
	  indicate the next line to be executed as the result of a
	  step or continue command. The debug cursor appears in the
	  left gutter of the source window containing the next line to
	  be executed.</para>

	<screenshot>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="images/debug_cursor.gif"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</screenshot>

	  <para>If the step or continue command advances the
	  program to a line that is not displayed in the current
	  source window, the JDEE opens the source file containing the
	  line, if necessary, and displays the source buffer in the
	  current source window, with the window scrolled to show the
	  line at which the program has halted.</para>

	<note>
	  <para>A blank source buffer indicates that the debugger
	    cannot find the source file into which you have stepped.
	    You should check your source path setting (see <ulink
	      url="#SettingSourcePath">Setting the Source
	      Path</ulink>) to ensure that it includes all source
	    files in the execution path of your program. 
	  </para>
	</note>
      </sect4>

    </sect3>

  </chapter>


  <chapter>

    <title><anchor id="SettingBreakpoints"/>Setting Breakpoints</title>

 
    <para>To set a breakpoint on any executable line in the current
      source buffer, click on the line and select <menuchoice>
	<guimenu>Jdb</guimenu>
	<guimenuitem>Set Breakpoint</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
      (<keycombo>
	<keycap>C</keycap>
	<keycap>c</keycap></keycombo><keycombo>
	<keycap>C</keycap>
	<keycap>a</keycap></keycombo>
	<keycombo>
	<keycap>C</keycap>
	<keycap>b</keycap></keycombo>).  The JDEE highlights the
      current line to indicate that a breakpoint is to be set at that
      line. </para>

    <screenshot>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/breakpoint.gif"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
    </screenshot>


    <para>
      If the debugger is
      running, the JDEE issues a command to the debugger to set a
      breakpoint at the highlighted line. If not, the JDEE issues the
      breakpoint command as soon as you start the debugger. If the
      class in which the breakpoint is to be set is currently in memory
      and the breakpoint is valid, the debugger sets the breakpoint.
      If the class in which the breakpoint is set is not in memory,
      the debugger puts it on a list of pending breakpoints. If the
      class is subsequently loades, the debugger sets the breakpoint
      in the class.
    </para>


    <sect3>
      <title><anchor id="BreakpointColors"/>Breakpoint Colors</title>
      
 
      <para>    
	The color of a breakpoint highlight indicates the status of the breakpoint
	as follows.
      </para>

      <table>
	<title>Breakpoint Colors</title>
	<tgroup cols="2">
	  <thead>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Color</entry>
	      <entry>Description</entry>
	    </row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Green</entry>
	      <entry>The JDEE has not yet issued a command to the
		debugger to set the breakpoint.</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Yellow</entry>
	      <entry>The breakpoint is pending loading of the class in which it
	      is to be set.</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Red</entry>
	      <entry>The breakpoint has been set.</entry>
	    </row>

	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>

    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title><anchor id="ClearingBreakpoints"/>Clearing
	Breakpoints</title>
      <para>
      To clear a breakpoint from a line in the current buffer, click
	on the line and select <menuchoice>
	  <guimenu>Jdb</guimenu>
	  <guimenuitem>Toggle Breakpoint</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
	(<keycombo>
	  <keycap>C</keycap>
	  <keycap>c</keycap></keycombo>
	  <keycombo>
	  <keycap>C</keycap>
	  <keycap>a</keycap></keycombo>
	<keycombo>
	  <keycap>C</keycap>
	  <keycap>b</keycap></keycombo>).
      </para>

      <para>To clear all breakpoints set in the current session,
	select <menuchoice><guimenu>Jdb</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Clear
	    Breakpoints</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
      </para>
 
      <note>
	<para>You can also set and clear breakpoints by entering jdb
	  breakpoint commands in the jdb interaction buffer. See the
	  jdb documentation for information on using the jdb
	  breakpoint commands.</para>
      </note>

    </sect3>
    
  </chapter>

  <chapter>

    <title><anchor id="SettingSourcePath"/>Setting the Source Path</title>

    <para>The <varname>jde-sourcepath</varname> variable specifies the
	directories the JDEE should search for source for classes
	visited by the debugger as you step through your program.
    </para>


    <para>To set this variable, enter <command>M-x customize-variable jde-sourcepath</command>.
      The customization buffer for jde-sourcepath appears. The buffer shows the current
      source path as a list of paths.</para>

      <screenshot>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/debug2.gif"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>To add a path, click the <guibutton>INS</guibutton> button
      corresponding to the position in the list and enter the path in
      the resulting edit field. To delete a path, click the <guibutton>DEL</guibutton> button
      corresponding to the path. You can use environment variables in paths and
      use dot notation to specify paths relative to the project file for the
      project to which this sourcepath applies. When you are done editing the buffer,
      press the <guibutton>State</guibutton> button to set the
      variable.</para>

      <para>To avoid having to specify the sourcepath every time you
      start a session, save the setting of
      <varname>jde-db-sourcepath</varname> in your
      <filename>prj.el</filename> file (see <ulink
	url="../jde-ug/jde-ug-content.html#SavingProjSettings">Saving
	Project Settings</ulink>)  To save the setting in your project
      file, select 
	<menuchoice>
	<guimenu>JDE</guimenu>
	<guimenuitem>Project</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Project File</guimenuitem>
	<guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem></menuchoice> (<keycombo>
	<keycap>C</keycap>
	<keycap>c</keycap>
      </keycombo>
      <keycombo>
	<keycap>C</keycap>
	<keycap>v</keycap>
      </keycombo>
      <keycombo>
	<keycap>C</keycap>
	<keycap>p</keycap>
      </keycombo>
      ). </para>


      <para>
      You must specify the paths of the top-level directories of any
      source code that you might visit while debugging your
      application. The source code directory structure must mirror
      your application's package structure. For example, suppose that your
      application includes a set of classes packaged in the
      <filename>myapp</filename> directory. Then, the source for those classes
      must be reside in a directory named <filename>myapp</filename> and you must
      specify the path of <filename>myapp</filename>'s parent directory.
      </para>

      <para>If you want to step through the JDK source code,
	select the source code install option when you install the JDK
	and set the <varname>jde-sourcepath</varname> variable
	to the top-level directory containing the source code.
	The JDE will use the JDK's package structure to find the
	source code in the subdirectories. </para>


  </chapter>


  <chapter>

    <title><anchor id="DisplayingVariables"/>Displaying Variables</title>

    <para>This section shows you how to display the values of variables
    (or expressions).</para>

    <sect3>

      <title><anchor id="DisplayingExpressions"/>Displaying
	Expressions</title>

      <para>When the debuggee program is stopped, the debugger lets
	you display the value of any valid Java expression composed of
	variables currently in scope.  For example, to display the
	value of a local, in-scope variable whose source is displayed
	in a Java source buffer, put the point on the variable and
	select
      <menuchoice>
	  <guimenu>Jdb</guimenu>
	  <guimenuitem>Display</guimenuitem>
	  <guimenuitem>Expression</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>. The JDEE prompts you to enter an expression to be
	evaluated and displayed in the minibuffer.</para>

      <screenshot>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/display_var1.gif"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot>


      <para> The default expression is the variable at point in the
	source buffer. Edit the displayed expression and press
	<keycap>Enter</keycap>. The JDEE issues a command to the
	debugger to display the variable in the jdb buffer.</para>

      <screenshot>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/display_var2.gif"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title><anchor id="DisplayingObjects"/>Displaying
	Objects</title>
      <para>To display the values of the fields of an object
	referenced by an in-scope variable in the current source
	buffer, and select
      <menuchoice>
	  <guimenu>Jdb</guimenu>
	  <guimenuitem>Display</guimenuitem>
	  <guimenuitem>Object</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>. The JDEE prompts you to enter the name of the
	variable in the minibuffer. The default is the variable at
	point in the source buffer. Press <keycap>Enter</keycap>. The
	JDEE issues a <command>dump</command> command to the debugger
	to display the field values of the object referenced by the
	variable you entered.</para>

      <screenshot>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/display_obj.gif"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </sect3>



    <sect3>
      <title><anchor id="DisplayingLocals"/>Displaying Locals
      </title>
      <para>To display the values of all in-scope local variables,
	including the values of the arguments of the method in which
	the program is halted, select
      <menuchoice>
	  <guimenu>Jdb</guimenu>
	  <guimenuitem>Display</guimenuitem>
	  <guimenuitem>Locals</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>. The JDEE issues a <command>locals</command>
	command to the debugger to display the local variable
	values.</para>

      <screenshot>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/display_locals.gif"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </sect3>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title><anchor id="SettingVariables"/>Setting Variables</title>
    
    <para>Jdb allows you to change the values of variables that are 
    in scope. To change the value of a variable via the JDEE's jdb
    interface:</para>

    <orderedlist>

      <listitem>
	<para>Position point on the variable you want to change.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Select <menuchoice>
	    <guimenu>Jdb</guimenu>
	    <guimenuitem>Set Variable</guimenuitem>
	  </menuchoice>.
	</para>
	<para>The JDEE prompts you to enter a left expression that
	  represents the variable whose value you want to change. The
	  default is the variable at point in the source buffer.
	</para>

	<screenshot>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="images/set_var1.gif"/>
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</screenshot>

	<note>
	  <para>Edit the expression if necessary. For example, to set
	    the value of an array element at point, edit the
	    expression to include the index of the element.</para>
	</note>

      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.</para>
	<para>The JDEE prompts you to enter the new value of the
	  variable.</para>

	<screenshot>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="images/set_var2.gif"/>
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</screenshot>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Enter the new value at the prompt in the minibuffer.</para>

	<screenshot>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="images/set_var3.gif"/>
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</screenshot>
      </listitem>
	

      <listitem>
	<para>Press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.</para>
	<para>The JDEE issues a <command>set</command> command to the
	  debugger to set the specified variable to the new
	  value.</para>

	<screenshot>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="images/set_var4.gif"/>
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</screenshot>

      </listitem>

    </orderedlist>

  </chapter>

  <chapter>

    <title><anchor id="DebugExternalProcesses"/>Debugging External Processes</title>

    <para>Normally jdb launches the application that it debugs.
      However, you can use jdb to debug processes that are not
      launched by jdb itself. This is useful, for example, if you need
      to debug a process running on a remote computer or a Java
      process launched by a nonJava process.</para>
    
    <para>Jdb provides two
      modes for debugging external processes: attach mode and listen
      mode. When started in attach mode, jdb connects itself to the
      external process. When started in listen mode, jdb waits for an
      external process to connect itself to jdb. Each mode has
      advantages. Attach mode allows you to debug an external process
      anytime after it has started. Listen mode allows you to debug
      the startup of a Java process launched by a nonJava process.</para>

    <para>
      The following sections explain how to use the JDEE's jdb
      interface to run jdb in attach and listen mode.</para>

    <sect3>
      <title><anchor id="AttachingProcesses"/>Attaching Processes</title>
      
      <para>To attach jdb to an external process, you must ensure that the 
      external process is started in debug server mode. You must then
      start jdb in attach mode.</para>

      <sect4>
	<title><anchor id="DebugServerMode"/>Starting the External
	  Process in Debug Server Mode</title>

	<para>To start an external process in debug server mode, you
	  must start the vm that runs the process with the following
	  command-line options:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><literal>-Xdebug</literal></para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <literal>-Xrunjdwp:transport=<keycap>TRANSPORT</keycap>,address=<keycap>ADDRESS</keycap>,server=y,suspend=<keycap>SUSPEND</keycap></literal>
	    </para>
	    <para>where</para> 
	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<para><literal><keycap>TRANSPORT</keycap></literal> is
		  the type of communications channel between jdb and
		  the debuggee process, either
		  <literal>dt_socket</literal> (socket) or
		  <literal>dt_shmem</literal> (shared memory, valid
		  only for Windows systems)</para>
		</listitem>
	      
	      <listitem>
		<para><literal><keycap>ADDRESS</keycap></literal> is
		  the address of the socket port or shared memory area
		  used by the debuggee process to listen for a jdb
		  connection.</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><literal><keycap>SUSPEND</keycap></literal> is
		  either <literal>y</literal> (suspend the debuggee
		  process at startup, i.e., to wait for jdb to start,
		  a useful option when you need to debug an
		  application's startup code) or <literal>n</literal>
		  (do not suspend the debuggee process)</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>	      
	  
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<example>
	  <title>Specifying Socket Transport</title>
	  <para><literal>-Xdebug
	      -Xrunjdwp:transport=dt_socket,address=4444,server=y,suspend=n</literal></para>
	</example>

	<example>
	  <title>Specifying Shared Memory Transport (MS Windows only)</title>
	  <para><literal>-Xdebug
	      -Xrunjdwp:transport=dt_shmem,address=javadebug,server=y,suspend=n</literal></para>
	</example>


	<para>The JDEE customization variable, <varname>jde-run-option-debug</varname>, causes
	the JDEE to generate these arguments automatically when launching a vm to run a  Java
	application. Thus, if you plan to launch the debuggee process from the JDEE, you
	should set this variable to the desired options.</para>
      </sect4>

      <sect4>
	<title><anchor id="AttachMode"/>Starting jdb in Attach
	  Mode</title>

	<para>To attach jdb to an existing process via a socket, 
	  select <menuchoice>
	    <guimenu>Jdb</guimenu>
	    <guimenuitem>External Process</guimenuitem>
	    <guimenuitem>Attach Via Socket</guimenuitem>
	  </menuchoice> from the Emacs menu bar. By default, 
	  the JDEE uses the socket address specified by 
	  the customization variable <varname>jde-db-option-connect-socket</varname>. 
	  If you set this variable to Prompt (nil), the JDEE 
	  prompts you to enter a socket address in the minibuffer. 
	</para>

	<note>
	  <para>The default socket address specified by
	    <varname>jde-db-option-connect-socket</varname>
	  is the same as the default socket address specified
	  by <varname>jde-run-option-debug</varname>. Thus, if you
	  want to attach jdb to a process started by the JDEE, the
	  only variable you have to set is 
	    <varname>jde-run-option-debug</varname> (to run 
	  the debuggee process in socket attach mode).</para>
	</note>


	<para>To attach jdb to an existing process via a shared memory
	  connection (Windows platforms only), 
	  select <menuchoice>
	    <guimenu>Jdb</guimenu>
	    <guimenuitem>External Process</guimenuitem>
	    <guimenuitem>Attach Via Shared Memory</guimenuitem>
	  </menuchoice> from the Emacs menu bar. By default, 
	  the JDEE uses the shared memory transport name specified by 
	  the customization variable 
	  <varname>jde-db-option-connect-shared-memory-name</varname>. 
	  If you set this variable to Prompt (nil), the JDEE 
	  prompts you to enter a shared-memory name in the minibuffer. 
	</para>

	<note>
	  <para>The default shared memory name specified by
	    <varname>jde-db-option-connect-shared-memory-name</varname>
	  is the same as the default shared memory name specified
	  by <varname>jde-run-option-debug</varname>. Thus, if you
	  want to attach jdb to a process started by the JDEE, the
	  only variable you have to set is 
	    <varname>jde-run-option-debug</varname> (to run 
	  the debuggee process in shared memory attach mode).</para>
	</note>

      </sect4>

    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title><anchor id="ListeningForProcesses"/>Listening for Processes</title>

      <para>To connect an external process to a jdb instance running in listener
      mode:</para>

      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Start jdb in listener mode (see <ulink url="#ListenMode">Starting
	    jdb in Listen Mode</ulink>)</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Start the debuggee process in debug client 
	    mode(see <ulink url="#DebugClientMode">Starting
	    the External Process in Debug Client Mode</ulink>)</para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <sect4>
	<title><anchor id="ListenMode"/>Starting jdb in Listen Mode</title>
	<para>To start jdb in listen mode, select <menuchoice>
	    <guimenu>Jdb</guimenu>
	    <guimenuitem>External Process</guimenuitem>
	    <guimenuitem>Listen For</guimenuitem>
	  </menuchoice> from the Emacs menu bar. By default, the 
	  JDEE prompts you to enter the address of the process to
	  be debugged in the minibuffer. The JDEE customization variable
	  jde-db-option-listen-address allows you to specify a default
	  debuggee address. If you set this variable, the JDEE does not
	  prompt you to enter an address.
	</para>

	<para>To start jdb listening for  existing process via a socket, 
	  select <menuchoice>
	    <guimenu>Jdb</guimenu>
	    <guimenuitem>External Process</guimenuitem>
	    <guimenuitem>Listen Via Socket</guimenuitem>
	  </menuchoice> from the Emacs menu bar. By default, 
	  the JDEE uses the socket address specified by 
	  the customization variable <varname>jde-db-option-connect-socket</varname>. 
	  If you set this variable to Prompt (nil), the JDEE 
	  prompts you to enter a socket address in the minibuffer. 
	</para>

	<note>
	  <para>The default socket address specified by
	    <varname>jde-db-option-connect-socket</varname>
	  is the same as the default socket address specified
	  by <varname>jde-run-option-debug</varname>. Thus, if you
	  want jdb to listen for a process started by the JDEE, the
	  only variable you have to set is 
	    <varname>jde-run-option-debug</varname>, i.e., to run 
	  the debuggee process in socket listen (client) mode.</para>
	</note>


	<para>To start jdb listening for a process via a shared memory
	  connection (Windows platforms only), 
	  select <menuchoice>
	    <guimenu>Jdb</guimenu>
	    <guimenuitem>External Process</guimenuitem>
	    <guimenuitem>Listen Via Shared Memory</guimenuitem>
	  </menuchoice> from the Emacs menu bar. By default, 
	  the JDEE uses the shared memory transport name specified by 
	  the customization variable 
	  <varname>jde-db-option-connect-shared-memory-name</varname>. 
	  If you set this variable to Prompt (nil), the JDEE 
	  prompts you to enter a shared-memory name in the minibuffer. 
	</para>

	<note>
	  <para>The default shared memory name specified by
	    <varname>jde-db-option-connect-shared-memory-name</varname>
	  is the same as the default shared memory name specified
	  by <varname>jde-run-option-debug</varname>. Thus, if you
	  want  jdb to listen for a process started by the JDEE, the
	  only variable you have to set is 
	    <varname>jde-run-option-debug</varname>, i.e., to run 
	  the debuggee process in shared memory listen (client) mode.</para>
	</note>
    
      </sect4>


      <sect4>
	<title><anchor id="DebugClientMode"/>Starting the External
	  Process in Debug Client Mode</title>

	<para>To start an external process in debug client mode, you
	  must start the vm that runs the process with the following
	  command-line options:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><literal>-Xdebug</literal></para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <literal>-Xrunjdwp:transport=<keycap>TRANSPORT</keycap>,address=<keycap>ADDRESS</keycap>,server=n,suspend=<keycap>SUSPEND</keycap></literal>
	    </para>
	    <para>where</para> 
	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<para><literal><keycap>TRANSPORT</keycap></literal> is
		  the type of communications channel between jdb and
		  the debuggee process, either
		  <literal>dt_socket</literal> (socket) or
		  <literal>dt_shmem</literal> (shared memory, valid
		  only for Windows systems)</para>
		</listitem>
	      
	      <listitem>
		<para><literal><keycap>ADDRESS</keycap></literal> is
		  the address of the socket port or shared memory area
		  used by jdb to listen for a debuggee process
		  connection.</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><literal><keycap>SUSPEND</keycap></literal> is
		  either <literal>y</literal> (suspend the debuggee
		  process when the connection occurs,
		  a useful option when you need to debug an
		  application's startup code) or <literal>n</literal>
		  (do not suspend the debuggee process)</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>	      
	  
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<example>
	  <title>Specifying Socket Transport</title>
	  <para><literal>-Xdebug
	      -Xrunjdwp:transport=dt_socket,address=4444,server=n,suspend=n</literal></para>
	</example>

	<example>
	  <title>Specifying Shared Memory Transport (MS Windows only)</title>
	  <para><literal>-Xdebug
	      -Xrunjdwp:transport=dt_shmem,address=javadebug,server=n,suspend=n</literal></para>
	</example>


	<para>The JDEE customization variable, <varname>jde-run-option-debug</varname>, causes
	the JDEE to generate these arguments automatically when launching a vm to run a  Java
	application. Thus, if you plan to launch the debuggee process from the JDEE, you
	should set this variable to the desired options.</para>

      </sect4>

    </sect3>

  </chapter>

  <chapter>

    <title><anchor id="DebugOptions"/>Debug Options</title>

    <para>The JDEE allows you to specify debug options by setting JDEE
      configuration variables. You can use the Emacs customization
      feature to set debug variables interactively. To use the
      customization feature, select <menuchoice>
	<guimenu>Project</guimenu>
	<guimenuitem>Options</guimenuitem>
	<guimenuitem>Debug</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the
      <guimenu>JDE</guimenu> menu. (See <ulink
	url="../jde-ug/jde-ug-content.html#ConfiguringJDE">Configuring
	the JDEE</ulink> for more information on using the
      customization feature). To save the compilation settings in the
      project file (see <ulink
	url="../jde-ug/jde-ug-content.html#UsingProjectFiles">Using
	Project Files</ulink> for the current source buffer, select
      <menuchoice>
	<guimenu>Project</guimenu>
	<guimenuitem>Project File</guimenuitem>
	<guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the
      <guimenu>JDE</guimenu> menu.</para>

    <para>The following table lists the jdb customization variables.</para>


    <table>

      <title>Jdb Customization  Variables</title>

      <tgroup cols="3">

	<thead>
	  <row>
	    <entry>Variable</entry>
	    <entry>Group</entry>
	    <entry>Usage</entry>
	  </row>
	</thead>

	<tbody>
    <row>
        <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-debugger</varname></entry>
        <entry valign="top">Project</entry>
        <entry valign="top">Specify which debugger to use to debug the current project.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
        <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-sourcepath</varname></entry>
        <entry valign="top">Project</entry>
        <entry valign="top">Specify location(s) of source files that
        can be visited while stepping through a program.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
        <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-db-mode-hook</varname></entry>
        <entry valign="top">Project</entry>
        <entry valign="top">Customization hook for jde-db inferior
        mode.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
        <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-global-classpath</varname></entry>
        <entry valign="top">Project</entry>
        <entry valign="top">Specify class paths for compile, run,
        and debug commands.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
        <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-db-read-vm-args</varname></entry>
        <entry valign="top">Project</entry>
        <entry>Specifies whether to read debugger VM arguments from
        the minibuffer.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
        <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-db-read-app-args</varname></entry>
        <entry valign="top">Project</entry>
        <entry>Specifies whether to read command-line application
        arguments from the minibuffer.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
        <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-db-option-classpath</varname></entry>
        <entry valign="top">Debug</entry>
        <entry valign="top">Specifies the classpath for the
        Java interpreter. This option overrides the
        jde-global-classpath option.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
        <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-db-option-verbose</varname></entry>
        <entry valign="top">Debug</entry>
        <entry valign="top">Print messages about the running
        process.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
        <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-db-option-properties</varname></entry>
        <entry valign="top">Debug</entry>
        <entry valign="top">Specify property values.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
        <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-db-option-heap-size</varname></entry>
        <entry valign="top">Debug</entry>
        <entry valign="top">Specify the initial and maximum size of
        the interpreter heap.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
        <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-db-option-stack-size</varname></entry>
        <entry valign="top">Debug</entry>
        <entry valign="top">Specify size of the C and Java stacks.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
        <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-db-option-garbage-</varname>
        <varname>collection</varname></entry>
        <entry valign="top">Debug</entry>
        <entry valign="top">Specify garbage collection
        options.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
        <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-db-option-java-profile</varname></entry>
        <entry valign="top">Debug</entry>
        <entry valign="top">Enable Java profiling.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
        <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-db-option-heap-profile</varname></entry>
        <entry valign="top">Debug</entry>
        <entry valign="top">Output heap profiling data.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
        <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-db-option-verify</varname></entry>
        <entry valign="top">Debug</entry>
        <entry valign="top">Verify classes.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
        <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-db-option-vm-args</varname></entry>
        <entry valign="top">Debug</entry>
        <entry valign="top">Specify command-line arguments to be
        passed to the Java VM.</entry>
    </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-db-option-application-args</varname></entry>
	    <entry valign="top">Debug</entry>
	    <entry valign="top">Specify command-line arguments to pass
	      to the application.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-db-option-connect-socket</varname></entry>
	    <entry valign="top">Debug</entry>
	    <entry valign="top">Specify socket address of a running process
	      to which you want to connect the debugger, using a
	      debugger attach or listen command.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-db-option-connect-shared-memory-name</varname></entry>
	    <entry valign="top">Debug</entry>
	    <entry valign="top">Specify shared memory name used by the debugger
	      to attach or listen for debuggee processes to debug.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry valign="top"><varname>jde-db-option-host</varname></entry>
	    <entry valign="top">Debug</entry>
	    <entry valign="top">Host of a remote process to which you
	      wish to attach the debugger. This option is invalid for JDK verions
	      greater than JDK 1.1.x.</entry>
	  </row>
	</tbody>      
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </chapter>

</book>

<!-- 
Local Variables: 
mode: xae
sgml-indent-step: 2
sgml-indent-data: t
sgml-set-face: t
sgml-insert-missing-element-comment: nil
End:
 -->