<?xml version="1.0"?>

<revision-log>
    <release version="2.4.0">
	<repo start-revision="83" end-revision="HEAD"/>
	<summary>
	    This is a "catchup" release that contains many patches and other
	    contributions that have been queuing up over the last few years.
	    While there are many new JDK 1.5 features added, the next (2.4.1)
	    release will contain more or hopefully the remainder of those
	    language changes.
	</summary>

	<change commiter="paullandes">
	    <msg>The old CVS Log entries have now moved to doc/history/cvs-revision-log.xml.</msg>
	</change>

	<change commiter="paullandes">
	    <msg>The release version is now dynamically updated in the source at build time.</msg>
	</change>

	<change commiter="paullandes">
	    <author>Ke Lu</author>
	    <author>Przemystaw Wojnowski</author>
	    <msg>Support for 1.5 generics and simplified for loops in jde-complete</msg>
	</change>

	<change commiter="lentrig">
	    <msg>More 1.5 and 1.6 support.</msg>
	</change>

	<change commiter="paullandes">
	    <author>Paul Landes</author>
	    <msg>jde-parse-get-buffer-class is now interactive and also returns class names sans packages.</msg>
	</change>

	<change commiter="paullandes">
	    <author>Paul Landes</author>
	    <msg>New addition of class driven bookmarks (jde-bookmark.el).</msg>
	</change>

	<change commiter="paullandes">
	    <author>Paul Landes</author>
	    <msg>More fontification (i.e. constructors).</msg>
	</change>

	<change commiter="paullandes">
	    <author>Paul Landes</author>
	    <msg>Beanshell can optionally display a separate buffer for errors based on customized variable `jde-bsh-separate-buffer'.</msg>
	</change>

	<change commiter="paullandes">
	    <author>Paul Landes</author>
	    <msg>New function `jde-parse-class-name' parses class name into package name parts so we don't have to pass around fully qualified type flags to functions that need this--i.e. source finding functions.</msg>
	</change>

	<change commiter="paullandes">
	    <author>Paul Landes</author>
	    <msg>New function `jde-read-class' provides better user input class finding.</msg>
	</change>

	<change commiter="paullandes">
	    <author>Paul Landes</author>
	    <msg>New function `jde-exception-goto' provides a way to go to a file and line number from an exception stack trace line..</msg>
	</change>

	<change commiter="paullandes">
	    <author>Paul Landes</author>
	    <msg>More robust jde-eval, which now doesn't get confused with extraneous show() output.  This feature can be turned off..</msg>
	</change>

	<change commiter="paullandes">
	    <author>Paul Landes</author>
	    <msg>More parsing ability (i.e. reverse camel notation parsing, which replaces some key bindings, convert from reverse camel notation to other variable formats like SQL, Java properties, hungarian notation, C constants, etc. parse Beanshell/Java expressions).</msg>
	</change>

    </release>

    <!--
	TODO add ReleaseNotes.txt for previous releases here and delete
	ReleaseNotes.txt
    -->
</revision-log>
